This just might be the single most underutilized training method among all lifters, and I think
I know why.
Long duration isometrics don't look impressive, and they're f***ing brutal.
You're not benching 405 or squatting 500 pounds, you're literally just not moving.
But don't confuse nothing moving with nothing happening.
Long duration isometrics can build serious strength and muscle.
They're also one of my favorite ways to expose weaknesses and compensations.
And here's the cool part.
The exercise that exposes the weakness can also help fix the weakness.
Isometrics can even have an analgesic effect.
I've had athletes with patella tendonitis feel noticeably better after just two sets
of iso hold lunges before training, and they're ridiculously versatile.
You can program them in your warmup, your main workout, as a finisher, on a recovery
day, even a stand alone workout.
Some of my personal favorites are iso hold lunges, low push up holds, superman or Y holds,
single leg back extension holds, and posterior chain planks.
So why doesn't everybody do them?
In my opinion, there's two main reasons.
Number one is ego, and two is discomfort.
Again, they don't look impressive.
And when you push an iso hold into the two, three, or four plus minute range, they are
absolutely f***ing miserable.
But sometimes the exercises that look like you're doing nothing are doing a hell of a
lot.
So I highly recommend including these into your training.
And if you want to try a program that intelligently incorporates long duration isometrics, check
out my lean bastard program at lean bastard.com.
This just might be the single most